# 哈喽大家好 我是王刚
Hello, everyone. I'm Wang Gang.
# 本期视频我跟大家分享一道家常菜
In this video I'm going to share a dish with you.
# 清蒸大闸蟹
Steamed hairy crab
# 大闸蟹下锅之前我们先用绳子将其捆住
Before we steam the crabs, we need to tie them up with rope.
# 将大闸蟹的蟹钳和蟹脚收缩起来
Put the hairy crab claws and legs in.
# 然后用绳子横着缠到第二圈
Then wrap the rope horizontally around for two loops.
# 再交叉纵向将其捆绑
Then cross vertically and tie it up.
# 这一步的目的是防止螃蟹蒸制的时候翻面
The purpose of this step is to prevent the crab from turning over while steaming.
# 也可以防止挣扎得时候断脚影响卖相
It also prevents crab legs from breaking during the struggle while steaming.
# 嫌麻烦的同学也可以交给摊主来处理
You can also leave the tying process to the vendor.
# 下一步开始准备辅料
Start preparing the other ingredients next.
# 准备生姜1小块切成姜片备用
Prepare 1 small piece of ginger cut into slices.
# 准备小葱1小把挽成节备用
Prepare 1 bunch of scallions and twist it into knot.
# 下一步开始蒸制
The next step is to start steaming.
# 锅中加入适量的清水
Add some water to the pot.
# 水的量可以适当的多加一些
The amount of water can be a bit more than usual
# 再将准备好的姜葱下入锅中
Then add the prepared ginger and scallions to the pot.
# 大火烧开之后将捆绑好的大闸蟹腹部朝上放入锅中
Place the hairy crabs belly side up in the pot over high heat.
# 盖上锅盖转中火蒸16分钟
Cover and steam over medium heat for 16 minutes.
# 16分钟之后揭开锅盖取出大闸蟹
After 16 minutes, take the crabs out.
# 剪断绳子之后下一步开始演示分解
Once the rope is cut, the next step is to demonstrate the breakdown process.
# 第一步我们先将大闸蟹的八爪以及钳子剪下
The first step is to cut off the eight legs and the claws of the hairy crab.
# 然后将8个爪子的两个关节剪掉
Then cut off two joints of the eight legs.
# 去掉关节之后用小叉子慢慢地往外面推出蟹腿肉
After removing the joint, use a small fork to slowly push out the crab leg meat.
# 将蟹钳放到墩上敲打
Place the crab claws on the pier and knock.
# 蟹钳敲碎之后再取出蟹肉
Crack the crab claws and then remove the crab meat.
# 同学们处理这一步的时候
During this step,
# 必须小心蟹钳上面的尖刺防止伤手
You must be careful of the spikes on the crab claws to prevent injury.
# 第二步将蟹身放在墩上
Then place the crab body on the pier.
# 用小锤敲打蟹壳的四周
Tap around the crab shell with the small hammer.
# 蟹背敲松之后用长柄斧打开蟹脐
After knocking the crab's back loose, use the long-handled axe to open the crab's abdomen.
# 然后撬开蟹壳
And then open the crab shell.
# 将蟹壳打开之后用镊子取出中间白色的蟹胃
After opening the crab shell and remove the white stomach with tweezers.
# 然后再翻过来取出黑膜底下白色的蟹心
Then flip it over and take out the white crab heart underneath the black membrane.
# 取出蟹胃和蟹心之后用剪子剪掉蟹嘴
After removing the crab stomach and heart and cut off the crab's mouth with scissors.
# 刮掉蟹鳃之后用勺子盛出蟹黄
After scraping off the gills, spoon out the crab roe (crab butter).
# 将蟹身从中间最薄的地方剪成两半
Cut the crab body in half from the thinnest part of the middle.
# 再用剪刀纵向剪成两边
And then cut it horizontally with scissors.
# 然后再用镊子将蟹身中间所有的蟹肉取出即可
Then use the tweezers to remove all the meat from the middle of the crab.
# 取出蟹肉之后下一步开始调料汁
After removing the crab meat, the next step is to prepare the sauce.
# 准备生姜1小块拍散之后剁碎备用
Prepare 1 small piece of ginger and chop it up.
# 碟中加入适量的香醋
Add some Zhenjiang vinegar to the small plate.
# 再加入少许的生抽酱油搅拌均匀即可
Add a bit soy sauce and mix well.
# 最后淋上适量的姜醋汁即可食用
Serve with a drizzle of ginger vinegar sauce.
# 下一步开始技术总结
Start the technical summary next.
# 第一
First,
# 用工具分解大闸蟹可以提高出肉率
Breaking down hairy crabs with tools can improve meat yield
# 蟹八件在普通超市或者某宝有售
The crab tools are available at Chinese supermarkets or online.
# 第二
Second,
# 大闸蟹也分公母
There are male and female hairy crabs.
# 母蟹产蟹黄 公蟹产蟹膏
Female crabs have crab roe (yellow), male crabs have crab paste (white).
# 一般来说农历九月的母蟹蟹黄最为肥美
Usually, female crabs are most delicious in the ninth month of the lunar calendar.
# 十月的公蟹蟹膏最为丰满
For male crabs, the tenth month of the lunar calendar is the best time.
# 第三
Third,
# 蟹肉性寒最好搭配姜汁或者黄酒食用中和寒性
Crab meat is cold in nature, best eaten with ginger or Chinese yellow wine to neutralize the coldness.
# 第四
Fourth,
# 辨别大闸蟹是否鲜活
To identify if hairy crabs are fresh and alive,
# 吐泡泡只能作为参考之一
the bubbles can be used as a reference.
# 也要看眼睛和爪子是否灵活
It also depends on how flexible the eyes and claws are.
# 清蒸大闸蟹的技术总结完毕
Steamed hairy crab technique summary is complete.